Guide to the New-York Historical Society Membership Records 1804-1983 NYHS-RG 9
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society membership records
1804-1983
New-York Historical Society
NYHS-RG 9
17.33 Linear feet in 113 volumes, six document boxes, and two oversize flat boxes.
The New-York Historical Society membership records includes material related to the basic administration of membership, that is, maintaining records of who was a member and whether their dues had been paid. The record group includes registers, or lists, of members, dues payment status, and certificates and other forms of membership-related ephemera.
Biographical/Historical Note
On November 20, 1804, eleven men met in the Picture Room of New York City's City Hall and decided to organize themselves into a "Society" to collect and preserve materials related to the history of the United States and particularly to the state of New York. Through 1805, this group and several additional men who joined the initiative, developed a Constitution and By-Laws, elected officers, issued a public appeal for new members, and took other steps to form the New-York Historical Society. By April 1806, N-YHS had 29 members who are considered the original, or founding, members. From this foundation, N-YHS's membership grew, with the number of dues-paying members reaching a few hundred by the end of the nineteenth century and into the twentieth.
There is a common thread over time in the meaning of membership in N-YHS: in exchange for financial support of the institution, a member was, and is, granted certain benefits in access to the collections, programs, and publications of the organization. But the differences over time are greater, and generally reflect the differences to be expected between an early nineteenth century private institution and a twenty-first century cultural enterprise open to the public.
One essential difference is that from the founding of N-YHS until 1938, members governed the institution. The members elected officers, formed the governing Executive Committee, took action on specific initiatives, represented N-YHS as delegates to other organizations, and voted on various management matters. Accordingly, the monthly membership meetings of N-YHS were a mix of business matters and program talks. Membership, therefore, was not broadly open to everyone. Although the procedure for accepting new members changed slightly over time, until 1917 candidates for membership needed to be nominated by a current member, approved by the Executive Committee, and elected by the members at the monthly meetings. From 1829 until about 1910, candidates could be refused admittance if three negative votes, or "black balls," were cast.
By the early twentieth century, though, various changes within N-YHS, society at large, and the evolving place of cultural institutions in society had influenced a movement away from this earlier model of a membership organization. Increasing amounts of authority were placed in the hands of N-YHS's governing Executive Committee until, in 1917, a by-law change eliminated the need for membership votes on any matters except for the election of officers. Prior to 1914, these elections had been held every year; a by-law change in 1914 extended the terms of office to three years. Consequently, after 1917, business meetings were held only every three years, and for narrow purposes. By-law changes in November 1937 completed the process of removing members from a governance and management role, and replacing the members' Executive Committee with an independent Board of Trustees that elected officers and new trustees. Despite this reduction in the organizational role of members, certain formalities associated with membership lingered until the late twentieth century. These included the continued "election" of new members by the Board and, until 1982, the publication in the Annual Report of the names of all newly-elected and current members and of those who had died during the prior year.
Although the size of N-YHS's membership grew considerably, it was not always steady. During the 1820s and 1830s, with no permanent home for its collections and membership gatherings, the organization faced declining membership and financial difficulties. A new home at New York University and new leadership in the early 1840s revitalized N-YHS and initiated intense efforts to recruit new and former members and to improve the membership and finances. Traces of these efforts can be found in this record group in the emergence from this period of member lists, collection receipt books, and other documents.
The documents here, especially the registers and payment records, also reflect N-YHS's efforts over time to at least maintain its membership levels, though often the adoption of new membership categories or dues and fees structures were aimed at increasing support. Over the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, N-YHS employed various categories of membership, each reflecting differences in associated required financial support and, to an extent, differences in access privileges. These differences are reflected in the various documentary forms, especially the registers, found in this record group. In its original 1805 Constitution, N-YHS established two categories of members: Resident Members (those residing in New York State) and Honorary Members (those residing elsewhere). Resident Members were required to pay $10 upon election, plus $2 annually thereafter; a one-time payment of $35 would make them Life Members, with commutation of the annual dues. Payments were optional for Honorary Members. Membership offered the significant privilege of being able to remove books from N-YHS's library for up to three months. The privilege of removing materials was ended in 1839, though members continued to have access to the materials in the library.
About 1825, annual dues increased from $2 to $4, and then to $5 in 1829, with an increase to $50 in the Life Member fee. In 1844, the categories of membership changed: Resident (those residing in New York City or the immediate vicinity), Corresponding (those residing elsewhere), and Honorary Members (those residing elsewhere that N-YHS wished to recognize with a membership). The "initiation fee" (a term introduced in 1853) for Resident Members was $10, which included a one-time $5 fee and $5 for the first years' dues, with $5 annual dues thereafter. A clause that Members could become Life Members by paying regularly for 15 successive years was added in 1844, but dropped within two years. Dues changed again in 1868 when Resident Members were required to pay a $20 fee for initiation and first year dues, and $10 annually thereafter, or a $100 fee for life membership.
In 1895, N-YHS ended the distinction, in place since 1805, between residents and non-residents. It eliminated the non-paying category of Corresponding Member, and included just one full category of membership, called simply Member. The initiation fee and annual dues remained at the 1868 levels. The Honorary category, reserved for special recognitions, also remained. In 1907, N-YHS adopted two new categories of membership, which encouraged and recognized larger contributions: Fellows ($1,000 donation) and Patrons ($5,000 donation). Both categories were life membership positions, and patrons had the right in perpetuity to appoint a successor, with some conditions (this benefit was later dropped for patrons joining after 1953). There was no change in the standard Member and Honorary Member categories. In 1918, another, non-paying category was added: Associate Member. Associates were to be elected in recognition of their historical research or other meritorious work in connection with American history. For example, this category was used in 1925 to admit all the members of the Naval History Society when its collection was transferred to N-YHS.
Aside from an important change in 1938, the membership categories and fees and dues established in 1907 and 1918 held until 1969. In 1938, the Member first year fee was reduced from $20 to $10; given that $10 was the annual dues amount, this change effectively ended the initiation fee, which had been in place since 1844. In 1963, in an explicit effort to widen its sources of income, N-YHS expanded its membership categories to include: Annual, or basic membership ($10 dues), Sustaining ($25 dues), Annual Fellow ($100 dues), Life ($250 one-time), Patron ($5,000 one-time), Sustaining Patron ($25,000 one-time), and Benefactor ($100,000 one-time). For the first time, N-YHS adopted a Corporate membership category, at $250; American Heritage Publishing Company and Time, Incorporated joined.
About 1967, the Fellows category was renamed Pintard Fellows. In 1968, the basic annual dues increased to $15, and then to $20 in 1972 and $25 in 1977. Also in 1972, a Research Member category with $10 dues was added, in part to mitigate the impact of a new $1 daily fee for library use by non-members. In 1982, when this record group closes, a new set of annual membership categories and fees were established: Friend ($1,000 and up), Pintard ($100 or more), Individual ($50), Family ($75), Senior ($25), and Student under 25 ($15). A Corporate membership fee was $1,000. One-time payment for life members was $5,000.
(Principal sources for the above were the various amended versions of N-YHS's Constitution and By-Laws, Annual Reports and R.W.G. Vail's Knickerbocker Birthday.)
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Scope and Contents Note
The New-York Historical Society membership records includes material related to the basic administration of membership, that is, maintaining records of who was a member and whether their dues had been paid. The record group includes registers, or lists, of members, dues payment status, and certificates and other forms of membership-related ephemera. The content principally includes volumes of lists of names, their category of membership (e.g., life, honorary, etc.), with addresses in some of the lists, and checklists and receipts documenting the payment or non-payment of dues. Some of the volumes hold newspaper clippings (mostly death notices) and occasional correspondence conveying notice of a member's resignation or death, though these are sparse. Many of the volumes have annotations noting death dates and changes in member status. The record group spans from entries reflecting the earliest members of 1804 (though the entries may not have been made then) to 1983, when the particular formats of the membership records maintained by the institution reflected here end. Much of the information in this record group can be gleaned from N-YHS's printed annual reports; indeed, much of the content of the annual member lists in Series II consists of clippings from the annual reports. Nevertheless, the documents, especially the Registers in Series I, provide a good overview of who constituted the membership of N-YHS, the dates of their election, and termination by death or resignation from N-YHS.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHS-RG Archives). Other record groups that are processed and available to researchers and are especially related to the New-York Historical Society membership records (NYHS-RG 9) are as follows:
The New-York Historical Society management committee records (NYHS-RG 1) includes the minute books of N-YHS member meetings and N-YHS's Executive Committee, from 1804-1938. These books include the recording of the nomination and election of new members. NYHS-RG 1 also holds so-called official papers which have many of the slips of paper and various forms used to submit a name for consideration for election to membership. Finally, NYHS-RG 1 holds some records related to identifying members and their dues status, especially for the 1840s.
The New-York Historical Society general correspondence record group (NYHS-RG 2) contains a variety of materials relating to N-YHS membership, including letters accompanying or inquiring about dues payments, recommendations of membership candidates and requests for consideration, acceptances and resignations of membership, personal information updates such as new addresses or death notices, and various other inquiries into the logistics, parameters, and requirements of membership. A limited amount of ephemera such as dues receipts and membership certificates are also present.
N-YHS's Print Room also has a collection of signed N-YHS membership certificates. These are available under the title of Certificate File, call number PR14.
Arrangement Note
The New-York Historical Society membership records (NYHS-RG 9) record group is organized in five series:
Series I. Registers
Series II. Annual Member Lists
Series III. Dues Collection Records
Series IV. Miscellaneous Lists
Series V. Certificates and Other Forms
Dues -- New York (State) -- New York.; Learned institutions and societies -- New York (State) -- New York -- Membership.; Libraries and institutions -- New York (State) -- New York -- Membership.; Bookkeeping registers; Certificates.; Clippings (information artifacts); Membership lists.; Receipts (financial records); Registers (lists); New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; New-York Historical Society -- Archives.; New-York Historical Society -- Membership.
- Series I. Registers, 1804-1983; 2.12 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents Note
  The Registers series includes two sets of volumes that together provide an index to members and their election dates and document their active (dues-paying) status. The date range for the series as a whole is extensive, running from 1804 to 1983, though one set of volumes has gaps.
  The first set of registers, called the Register of Members, includes two volumes, the first running from 1804-1901, the second from 1902-1982. The registers record the names of members in the chronological order of their election. The particular status (honorary, corresponding, life, etc.) is noted. Members from outside of New York state are noted as such. Addresses are included for all members beginning in 1920. Especially useful is that each volume also includes a rough alphabetical index of members, indicating the page number of the volume on which can be found the record of their election to the Society. The entries begin in 1804 with N-YHS's first meeting, though it seems likely the earliest years were recorded after the fact.
  The second set of registers, called the Treasurer's Register, includes records indicating the actual payment of dues, or lack of payment, by members. The date range is from the early 1840s to 1983, though there are gaps, especially for the 1940s and 1950s. The volumes list members alphabetically, indicating their payments over time; each volume covers specific periods (e.g., 1890-1899). The earliest volumes take a somewhat different form but include the same basic information as the later volumes. Generally, the Treasurer's Registers include only member names and amount paid.
  Arrangement Note
  The two volume Register of Members begins the series, followed by the various Treasurer's Registers and other records of dues payments, with each volume proceeding in chronological order.
  - Register of Members, 1804-1901 (Volume RG9.1, Folder -)
  - Register of Members, 1902-1982 (Volume RG9.2, Folder -)
  - Treasurer's Register, 1838-1840, 1851-1855 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Treasurer's Register, 1848-1850 (Volume RG9.3, Folder -)
  - Treasurer's Register, 1855-1964 (Volume RG9.4, Folder -)
  - Treasurer's Register, 1860-1869 (Volume RG9.5, Folder -)
  - Treasurer's Register, 1868-1876 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Treasurer's Register, 1870-1879 (Volume RG9.6, Folder -)
  - Treasurer's Register, 1880-1889 (Volume RG9.7, Folder -)
  - Treasurer's Register, 1890-1899 (Volume RG9.8, Folder -)
  - Treasurer's Register, 1900-1909 (Volume RG9.9, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents from Treasurer's Register, 1908-1909 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes documents found loose inside the covers of the Treasurer's Register for 1900-1909, including notes on member mailings concerning dues, dues in arrears, and a summary of dues collected from annual and life members 1868-1908. Includes a public "circular of information" describing the N-YHS galleries, circa 1909.
  - Treasurer's Register, 1910-1919 (Volume RG9.10, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents from Treasurer's Register, 1915-1918 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes documents found loose inside the covers of the Treasurer's Register for 1910-1919, including unpaid dues lists. Includes part of a catalogue of print matter from Goodspeed's Book Shop of Boston, with annotations.
  - Treasurer's Register, 1920-1929 (Volume RG9.11, Folder -)
  - Treasurer's Register, 1930-1939 (Volume RG9.12, Folder -)
  - Treasurer's Register, 1960-1964 (Volume RG9.13, Folder -)
  - Dues Record. Annual Members, 1964-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dues Record. Sustaining Members, 1964-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dues Record. Pintard Fellows, 1964-1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Dues Record. Research Members, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Dues Record. Annual Members (1 of 3), 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dues Record. Annual Members (2 of 3), 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Dues Record. Annual Members (3 of 3), 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Dues Record. Pintard Fellows, 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dues Record. Corporate Members, 1964-1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Dues Record. Friends and Family, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Dues Record. Seniors, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Dues Record. Student Members, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Log of Dues Daily Receipts, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series II. Annual Member Lists, 1873-1978; 6.92 Linear feet
  The Annual Member Lists series includes 69 volumes of member lists. The volumes are essentially scrapbooks. From 1912 to the end of the series in 1978, each volume includes the year's list of members as cut and pasted from the N-YHS printed annual report. These lists include annotations concerning deaths, resignations, and other factors impacting membership status that occurred during the year. Newspaper clippings, especially death notices and obituaries, and some correspondence concerning resignations and deaths, are glued into the volumes. The earliest years in the series—1873 to 1911—are compiled in three volumes; these are a bit less consistent in content than the later years, with many more handwritten annotations, but include essentially the same information.
  The Annual Member Lists series is arranged chronologically. The first three volumes include several years of lists, sometimes overlapping. Most of the subsequent volumes (1912 and later) include only one year per volume.
  Some of the clippings in the volumes have detached from the pages, and others are likely to do so over time. These loose documents are found in a folder in a box separate from the volume, as noted in the container list. Given the likelihood of more documents coming detached over time, labeled, but currently empty, folders have been included in the boxes with folders containing documents. These empty folders, though found in the boxes and available for future use, are not noted in the public version of the container list.
  - Member List, 1873-1895 [1898] (Volume RG9.14, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1898 [1892]-1905 (Volume RG9.15, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1898-1905 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Member List, 1906-1911 (Volume RG9.16, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1906-1911 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Member List, 1912 (Volume RG9.17, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Member List, 1913 (Volume RG9.18, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Member List, 1914 (Volume RG9.19, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Member List, 1915 (Volume RG9.20, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Member List, 1916 (Volume RG9.21, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Member List, 1917 (Volume RG9.22, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1918 (Volume RG9.23, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Member List, 1919 (Volume RG9.24, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Member List, 1920 (Volume RG9.25, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Member List, 1921 (Volume RG9.26, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1922 (Volume RG9.27, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1923 (Volume RG9.28, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1924 (Volume RG9.29, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Member List, 1925 (Volume RG9.30, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Member List, 1926-1927 (Volume RG9.31, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Member List, 1928 (Volume RG9.32, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Member List, 1929 (Volume RG9.33, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Member List, 1930 (Volume RG9.34, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1931 (Volume RG9.35, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Member List, 1932 (Volume RG9.36, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1933 (Volume RG9.37, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Member List, 1934 (Volume RG9.38, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Member List, 1935 (Volume RG9.39, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Member List, 1936 (Volume RG9.40, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Member List, 1937 (Volume RG9.41, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Member List, 1938 (Volume RG9.42, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1939 (Volume RG9.43, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1940 (Volume RG9.44, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1941 (Volume RG9.45, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1942 (Volume RG9.46, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1943 (Volume RG9.47, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1944 (Volume RG9.48, Folder -)
    Includes an 8x10 photograph of Director Alexander J. Wall.
  - Member List, 1945 (Volume RG9.49, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Member List, 1946 (Volume RG9.50, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1947 (Volume RG9.51, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1948 (Volume RG9.52, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1949 (Volume RG9.53, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Member List, 1950 (Volume RG9.54, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1951 (Volume RG9.55, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Member List, 1952 (Volume RG9.56, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Member List, 1953 (Volume RG9.57, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1954 (Volume RG9.58, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1955 (Volume RG9.59, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1956 (Volume RG9.60, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1957 (Volume RG9.61, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1958 (Volume RG9.62, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Member List, 1959 (Volume RG9.63, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1960 (Volume RG9.64, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Member List, 1961 (Volume RG9.65, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1962 (Volume RG9.66, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1963 (Volume RG9.67, Folder -)
  - Member List, 1964 (Volume RG9.68, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Member List, 1965 (Volume RG9.69, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Member List, 1966 (Volume RG9.70, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Member List, 1967 (Volume RG9.71, Folder -)
  - Loose Documents, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Member List, 1968 (Volume RG9.72, Folder -)